<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HEALIS</title>
    <link>https://healis.eu/en/</link>
    <description>Recent content on HEALIS</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; HEALIS - Athanassios I. Hatzis, {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://healis.eu/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HyperMorph</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/hmorph/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/hmorph/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/about/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All Posts in Descending Chronological Order</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/post/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/post/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms of Use</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By accessing, browsing, or using this Web site, you acknowledge that you have read, understood, and agree to be bound by these terms and to comply with all applicable laws and regulations. If you do not agree to these terms, please do not use this Web site. HEALIS may, without notice to you, at any time revise these Terms of Use and any other information contained in this Web site by updating this posting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;disclaimer-of-warranty&#34;&gt;Disclaimer of Warranty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;USE OF THIS SITE IS AT YOUR SOLE RISK. ALL MATERIALS, INFORMATION, PRODUCTS, SOFTWARE, PROGRAMS, AND SERVICES ARE PROVIDED &amp;ldquo;AS IS,&amp;rdquo; WITH NO WARRANTIES OR GUARANTEES WHATSOEVER. HEALIS EXPRESSLY DISCLAIMS TO THE FULLEST EXTENT PERMITTED BY LAW ALL EXPRESS, IMPLIED, STATUTORY, AND OTHER WARRANTIES, GUARANTEES, OR REPRESENTATIONS, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE, AND NON-INFRINGEMENT OF PROPRIETARY AND INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS. WITHOUT LIMITATION, HEALIS MAKES NO WARRANTY OR GUARANTEE THAT THIS WEB SITE WILL BE UNINTERRUPTED, TIMELY, SECURE, OR ERROR-FREE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YOU UNDERSTAND AND AGREE THAT IF YOU DOWNLOAD OR OTHERWISE OBTAIN MATERIALS, INFORMATION, PRODUCTS, SOFTWARE, PROGRAMS, OR SERVICES, YOU DO SO AT YOUR OWN DISCRETION AND RISK AND THAT YOU WILL BE SOLELY RESPONSIBLE FOR ANY DAMAGES THAT MAY RESULT, INCLUDING LOSS OF DATA OR DAMAGE TO YOUR COMPUTER SYSTEM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOME JURISDICTIONS DO NOT ALLOW THE EXCLUSION OF WARRANTIES, SO THE ABOVE EXCLUSIONS MAY NOT APPLY TO YOU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;limitation-of-liability&#34;&gt;Limitation of Liability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IN NO EVENT WILL HEALIS BE LIABLE TO ANY PARTY FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY TYPE WHATSOEVER RELATED TO OR ARISING FROM THIS WEB SITE OR ANY USE OF THIS WEB SITE, OR OF ANY SITE OR RESOURCE LINKED TO, REFERENCED, OR ACCESSED THROUGH THIS WEB SITE, OR FOR THE USE OR DOWNLOADING OF, OR ACCESS TO, ANY MATERIALS, INFORMATION, PRODUCTS, OR SERVICES, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, ANY LOST PROFITS, BUSINESS INTERRUPTION, LOST SAVINGS OR LOSS OF PROGRAMS OR OTHER DATA, EVEN IF HEALIS IS EXPRESSLY ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES. THIS EXCLUSION AND WAIVER OF LIABILITY APPLIES TO ALL CAUSES OF ACTION, WHETHER BASED ON CONTRACT, WARRANTY, TORT, OR ANY OTHER LEGAL THEORIES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-terms&#34;&gt;Additional Terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional or different terms, conditions, and notices may apply to specific materials, information, products, software, and services offered through this Web site. In the event of any conflict, such additional or different terms, conditions, and notices will prevail over these Terms of Use. Please see the applicable agreement or notice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All Talks in Descending Chronological Order</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R3DM/S3DM</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/s3dm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/s3dm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/publication/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ztemps</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/ztemp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/ztemp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
