<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Authors on HEALIS</title>
    <link>https://healis.eu/en/authors/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Authors on HEALIS</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; HEALIS - Athanassios I. Hatzis, {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://healis.eu/en/authors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Athanassios I. Hatzis is a seasoned IT professional, showcasing a blend of technical expertise, proficiency in software engineering, and strong leadership. His project management skills, particularly highlighted as an IT Work Package Manager in EC FP7, are complemented by a rich background in research and academia. With over two decades of experience in the IT sector, Athanassios has demonstrated a strategic mindset, adept at making trade-off decisions considering desirability, viability, and technical feasibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serving as the software architect at major USA marathon events, Athanassios has showcased his ability to manage and execute agile development work effectively. He has been instrumental in establishing, deploying, and securely operating back-end systems and services across their full software life cycle. His strategic planning and resource allocation have been key in ensuring the smooth operation of these events, demonstrating proactive problem-solving in both technical and managerial aspects.
During his tenure as Health Informatics Manager at Evangelismos General Hospital, Athanassios effectively managed facilities and IT infrastructure implementing electronic medical records and cutting-edge clinical information systems. He developed strategies and organised work activities, demonstrating his strong organizational and managerial skills. His commitment to network and database security policy ensured the protection of sensitive medical information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pioneer in innovative technologies for the semantic web within startup ventures, Athanassios&amp;rsquo;s dedication to fostering creative and collaborative thinking is evident. His role as a researcher and lecturer is manifested by numerous published papers and presentations at conferences, contributing significantly to the academic discourse in health informatics and speech technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond technical expertise, Athanassios’s social and communication skills are well-developed, with experience in methodical leadership, delegation of responsibilities, and effectively liaising with diverse stakeholders, including speech therapists, medical staff, project managers, development teams, IT support staff, startup members and software vendors. Notably, his communication skills have been enriched by his interactions with students and lecturers in various higher education institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His thoughtful decision-making and rigorous adherence to best practices, coupled with his ability to adapt to changing circumstances, consistently result in exceptional execution performance in dynamic and challenging environments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Ford</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/authors/robert-ford/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/authors/robert-ford/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
