<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Information on HEALIS</title>
    <link>https://healis.eu/en/tags/information/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Information on HEALIS</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; HEALIS - Athanassios I. Hatzis, {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://healis.eu/en/tags/information/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Plerophoria vs Information</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/post/20150523/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/post/20150523/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;information&#34;&gt;Information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origin of the word information reveals its use. Inform comes from the Latin verb informare, which literally means to give form, or to form an idea. Form is the mold, the container, that is used to give shape, to molten the content. When computer scientists were designing and constructing the first digital computer, at the same time digital information was given birth and shape. Modern computers operate with memory chips and those are mere containers of storing sequences of 0s and 1s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;plērophoria&#34;&gt;Plērophoria&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above interpretation and use of the word information is typical of western culture way of thinking. Although it is convenvient to keep things in boxes, Eastern philosophers used to think differently. The ancient and modern Greek word for information is &lt;code&gt;πληροφορία&lt;/code&gt;, which transliterates (plērophoria) from πλήρης (plērēs) “fully” and φέρω (phorein) frequentative of (pherein) to carry through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It literally means &amp;ldquo;bears fully&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;conveys fully&amp;rdquo;. In modern Greek the word Πληροφορία is still in daily use and has the same meaning as the word information in English&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This contrasting use and interpretation of the word plerophoria traces its roots back to Socrates, Plato, and Aristotle’s theory of semiosis. In this regard every word plays the role of a symbol, i.e. sign that can be interpreted to communicate information to the one decoding that specific type of sign. There is an intimate and inseperable connection of the signified, i.e. the concept whose meaning the interpretant attempts to decode, with the signifier, i.e. sign’s physical form such as the sound of a word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every bit of digital information, i.e. 0 or 1 assimilates this triadic relationship. Bits are symbols signified as true or false taking the form of input voltage (signifier). The infinite combination of sequences of such symbols gives us the power to represent anything digitally. Their meaning depends on how we interpret these sequences, as numbers, letters, sounds, color, or anything else that can be encoded. The form of the signifier is not limited to that of a mere container that stores a sequence of 0s and 1s. It is a fully functional level of abstraction connected to higher and lower levels by applying recursively the theory of semiosis until we reach CPU’s binary level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-turing-machine&#34;&gt;The Turing Machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One-tape Turing machine according to Hopcroft and Ullman can be formally defined as a 7-tuple. Elements of this tuple are members of three distinct sets. A non-empty set of tape alphabet symbols, e.g. {0, 1}, a non-empty set of states, e.g. {A, B, C, HALT} and a set of state transitions e.g. {L, R}. Turing machine reads the tape symbols and executes a sequence of instructions according to a state table. Although this is not the space and time to adapt the theory of semiosis on the Turing machine we can clearly see an analogy. The tape symbol plays the role of a sign, the signified instruction is executed according to the interpretation given by the state table, and there is the physical form it takes as a printed text symbol on a white square of a paper tape. You can apply the same logic to the set of states and the set of transitions because these are symbols (signs) too; they can be interpreted and realized in some other physical or non-physical form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;r3dms3dm-abstraction-mechanism&#34;&gt;R3DM/S3DM Abstraction Mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In digital representation of information we can define a chain of interpretations, representations and realizations that are built in a consecutive order. This chain of semiosis reveals the mechanism that we can use to build higher levels of abstraction. At each step the symbol that is used to link together the signifier with the signified can become a fundamental unit, i.e. signifier to build the next level of abstraction. Thus we can move in two directions, we can generalize or we can specialize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5883270314305028098&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140613 Computational Semiotics - Information vs Plerophoria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/plerophoria-vs-information-athanassios-i-hatzis-phd/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20150523 Article - Plerophoria vs Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information#Etymology&#34;&gt;Etymology section&lt;/a&gt; of the term Information was updated by user Healis with the quoted text above on the 13th of June 2014 &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S3DM/R3DM</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#computational-semiotic-triangle&#34;&gt;Computational Semiotic Triangle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-core-terms-of-s3dmr3dm&#34;&gt;The Core Terms of S3DM/R3DM&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sterms&#34;&gt;STerms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#rterms&#34;&gt;RTerms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#other-terms&#34;&gt;Other Terms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#trilateral-relations&#34;&gt;Trilateral Relations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#s3dmr3dm-dogma&#34;&gt;S3DM/R3DM Dogma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#s3dmr3dm-formalization-v20&#34;&gt;S3DM/R3DM Formalization v2.0&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#memorizing-the-formula&#34;&gt;Memorizing the formula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#s3dmr3dm-formalization-v10&#34;&gt;S3DM/R3DM Formalization v1.0&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-trilateral-principle&#34;&gt;The Trilateral Principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#symbols-duality-principle&#34;&gt;Symbol&amp;rsquo;s Duality Principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-threefold-tower-of-babel-in-information-technology&#34;&gt;The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S3DM/R3DM is a conceptual framework that formalizes the architectural design of data modeling process in software engineering. It is founded on the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sign_(semiotics)&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Sign&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from Ancient to Modern Semiotics. S3DM/R3DM framework is based on the powerful theory of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triangle_of_reference&#34;&gt;semiotic triangle&lt;/a&gt;, a.k.a triangle of reference. We use numerical vectors (&lt;code&gt;signs&lt;/code&gt;), to encode abstract things in our mind (&lt;code&gt;signified&lt;/code&gt;) to which the sign refers, e.g. Person, name, Car, model. We associate these with data containers-forms that the sign takes for the storage of data values (&lt;code&gt;signifier&lt;/code&gt;), i.e. primitive data types (see wikipedia &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signified_and_signifier&#34;&gt;Signified and Signifier&lt;/a&gt; article). This trilateral principle of S3DM/R3DM framework permits a uniform treatment of &lt;strong&gt;semantics&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;syntax&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;storage&lt;/strong&gt; of information based on a symbolic representation. Next we define a fundamental, &lt;strong&gt;atomic information resource unit&lt;/strong&gt;, (AIR). Those units, in turn, can be easily shaped to form any tabular, hierarchical, or graph data structure in a unified way. Data granularity can be also deeply connected and related to the definition of a fundamental unit of processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;computational-semiotic-triangle&#34;&gt;Computational Semiotic Triangle&lt;/h2&gt;








  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-triangles&#34; href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/1.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/1_hu36aa7f76864557f3365108584961a105_72807_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-triangles&#34; href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/2.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/2_hu21e291047e3aff5b1aa1a72857386392_434705_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-triangles&#34; href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/3.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/3_hu51a099ed62fa0c4ab18c6aa77bd260ce_417813_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-triangles&#34; href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/4.jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/4_hu892b8cab1a2bc8a100e1abb73c5314bf_1111011_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-triangles&#34; href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/5..jpg&#34; &gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/r3dm/triangles/5._hue8fd63799a17e9a13e3af2a06cce3c19_414369_0x190_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  

  
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First illustration with porsche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second illustration with
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information representation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information realization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third illustration with
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;computer storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration with real-world object (green leaves)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Illustration with an event (traffic lights)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-core-terms-of-s3dmr3dm&#34;&gt;The Core Terms of S3DM/R3DM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two sets of base terms one starting with the letter &amp;lsquo;R&amp;rsquo; and the other with the letter &amp;lsquo;S&amp;rsquo; that we can use in order to convey the fundamental principles of R3DM. Both of the sets are outlined hierarchically into three levels. Each level is described with one or more characteristic words that are useful for memorizing and recapitulating the distinguishing features of R3DM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sterms&#34;&gt;STerms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S3 : Signified, Sense, Semantic - Signify&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signified, in Greek &amp;ldquo;σημαινόμενον&amp;rdquo;, to mean something&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S2 : Sign, Symbol, Syntax, Structure - SymbolizeS2 : Sign, Symbol, Syntax, Structure - Symbolize&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sign, in Greek &amp;ldquo;σημείο&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S1 : Signifier, Storage (String) - Store&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signifier, in Greek &amp;ldquo;σημαίνον&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rterms&#34;&gt;RTerms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R3 : Information Resource - InfoRes (Enity) - Originate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R2 : Information Representation - InfoRes (Symbol) - Represented&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R1 : Information Realization (Datum) - Realized&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-terms&#34;&gt;Other Terms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also other terms that are often used when we describe relations, operations and features in R3DM these are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Referenced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interpreted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formatted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expressed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decoded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encoded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parsed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;trilateral-relations&#34;&gt;Trilateral Relations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trilateral schema of relations between R1, R2 and R3 or equally between S1, S2, S3 defines the core mechanism of semiosis. We will use the terms we defined in previous section to build simple sentences that convey the full meaning. We will also use three prepositions &amp;ldquo;from&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;through&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;in&amp;rdquo; that accompany RTerms and STerms in a specific order that signifies the left to right direction of abstraction&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direction from S1 through S2 in S3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data from S1 are Symbolized through S2 and Signified in S3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data from S1 are Decoded through S2 and Interpreted in S3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realization from S1 is Parsed through S2 and Interpreted in S3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direction from S3 through S2 in S1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Resources from S3 are Represented through S2 and Realized in S1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Resources from S3 are Represented through S2 and Encoded in S1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Resources from S3 are Represented through S2 and Formatted in S1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;


&lt;button class=&#34;btn  btn-warning&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;  &gt; An Interpretation from S3 is Symbolized through S2 and Formatted in S1 &lt;/button&gt;



&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;


&lt;button class=&#34;btn  btn-warning&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;  &gt; Information Resources from S3 are Symbolized through S2 and Stored in S1 &lt;/button&gt;



&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;s3dmr3dm-dogma&#34;&gt;S3DM/R3DM Dogma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the term dogma we want to bring together a set of R3DM principles laid down by an authority as incontrovertibly true. R3DM dogma serves as part of the primary basis of R3DM modelling system, and it cannot be changed or discarded without affecting the very system&amp;rsquo;s paradigm. R3DM is serving one purpose to become the paradigm of paradigms, the metamodel of metamodels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;s3dmr3dm-formalization-v20&#34;&gt;S3DM/R3DM Formalization v2.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S3DM/R3DM is a conceptual model of an information processing system based on semiosis. S3DM/R3DM fundamental construct is the uniform information &lt;strong&gt;RESOURCE (UIR)&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e. a parent class of the following three derived subclasses :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Term Information Resource (TIR)&lt;/strong&gt; models any concept, subject, topic, idea at a highest level, S3, i.e. sense, context level, of abstraction. TIR is also called the signified information resource&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the next, intermediate level, S2 - sign level, a &lt;strong&gt;Sign Information Resource (SIR)&lt;/strong&gt;, models the notion of the sign in semiotics. Therefore (TIR) is &lt;strong&gt;REPRESENTED&lt;/strong&gt; by (SIR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally at level, S1, i.e. data level, (SIR) conveys information that are encoded inside a data container, i.e. &lt;strong&gt;Datum Information Resource (DIR)&lt;/strong&gt;, signifier. The content inside (DIR), i.e. data, is expressed with an atomic or complex data structure and &lt;strong&gt;REALIZED&lt;/strong&gt; with operations on data. Therefore &lt;strong&gt;(SIR) is REALIZED by (DIR)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all the levels, S3, S2, S1 of abstraction references are created and maintained for the context of the signified concept (S3), the construction of signs (S2), and for the addressing of containers and the indexing of content that express signifiers (S1). Thus, information resources are &lt;strong&gt;REFERENCED&lt;/strong&gt; differently depending on the level of abstraction by a &lt;strong&gt;Reference Information Resource (RIR)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a hidden level S0, machine-system level, where everything is encoded and expressed with a sequence of binary digits but this currently out of our scope.&lt;/p&gt;






&lt;figure class=&#34;alignleft&#34;&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;r3dm_formalization_v2.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;memorizing-the-formula&#34;&gt;Memorizing the formula&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a concise way S3DM/R3DM can be described in any of the following memorable ways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3DM/R3DM Edges - Duality of Sign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any Sign at level S2 is correlated to a Signifier at level S1 and the Signified at level S3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3DM/R3DM Nodes - Triadic Relationship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any information RESOURCE at level S3 can be REPRESENTED at level S2 and REALIZED at level S1 using a different REFERENCE mechanism at each level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3DM/R3DM Nodes - Triadic Relationship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information RESOURCES are REPRESENTED, REALIZED and REFERENCED&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3DM/R3DM Nodes - Triadic Relationship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information RESOURCES are originated FROM level S3, are represented THROUGH level S2 and encoded IN level S1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;s3dmr3dm-formalization-v10&#34;&gt;S3DM/R3DM Formalization v1.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact it occurs that this formalization is also the first attempt to formalize the notion of the word “plerophoria”, i.e. information translated in Greek, using Aristotle’s semiotic triangle of meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S3DM/R3DM models any concept C at a highest level, L2, of abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information RESOURCES about that concept are REPRESENTED and consequently encoded using a combination of signs S at an intermediate level, L1, into a message M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then at the lowest level, L0, the content of M is expressed with a complex data structure D and REALIZED with operations on data containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all L0, L1, L2 levels of abstraction, we maintain REFERENCES for the context (L2), for the construction of signs (L1), and for the addressing of containers and the indexing of content (L0).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-trilateral-principle&#34;&gt;The Trilateral Principle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resource, symbol and data, each plays a distinct role but they are united with a trilateral relationship and act as one thing. They are present at every level of R3DM as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;

&lt;button class=&#34;btn  btn-warning&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;  &gt; Signified - Sign - Signifier &lt;/button&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;

&lt;button class=&#34;btn  btn-warning&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;  &gt; Resource - Representation - Realization &lt;/button&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact you cannot separate these three things in any computer engineering architecture, the signifier (the concept, semantics), the symbol (serialization, syntax), and the signified (storage, data form, i.e. strings, numbers, bits). They stay together from the lowest level of abstraction, to the highest level. You can only link these meaning triangles side by side and move in two directions, specialization or generalization, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jfsowa.com/ontology/ontometa.htm&#34;&gt;Sowa Ontology, Metadata, and Semiotics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;symbols-duality-principle&#34;&gt;Symbol&amp;rsquo;s Duality Principle&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;button class=&#34;btn  btn-warning&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;  &gt; EVERYTHING is represented with a symbol &lt;/button&gt;



&lt;p&gt;There is a duality on the characteristics of a sign. Symbols play two roles at the same time that of a container and content. These roles cannot be separated, they always come in pairs. You may think in terms of how computer memory works to understand this. In digital computers &lt;strong&gt;EVERYTHING is represented with a sequence of bits&lt;/strong&gt;, but this sequence is stored in an array of memory cells. Therefore any such fundamental construct, i.e. data structure, that can be build at a higher level should comply with a symmetrical design, i.e. Types, Instances, Values, and Relations-Associations all of them have to be constructed from these atomic fundamental constructs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-threefold-tower-of-babel-in-information-technology&#34;&gt;The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A concise synopsis of the chaotic situation that is present in information technology is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user is experiencing a threefold Tower of Babel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in semantic web and linked data - conceptual modelling,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in computer programming - symbolic modelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in persistent or temporary storage and retrieval of information - data modelling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;






&lt;figure class=&#34;alignleft&#34;&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;babel.jpg&#34; &gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;%7B%7Bbase_path%7D%7D/r3dm_project/post000000/&#34;&gt;HEALIS   - 20120920 Ignite Athens 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-275236266&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130920 Topic Maps Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/60636/60636-275239328&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130920 Linked Data Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/38506/38506-275240136&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130920 Semantic Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/73235/73235-275241358&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130920 Database Developers and Architects Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/60636/60636-275742535&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130923 Linked Data Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-276331243&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130925 Semantic Web Research - URI Identity Crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-277065814&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130927 Semantic Web Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5812169398596702208&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131129 Computational Semiotics - The Variable-Value Pair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5812182372547850240&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131129 Semantic Web Research - The Variable-Value Pair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-5812199358258520066&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131129 Topic Maps Community - The loss of interest in Topic Maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5814353290581803012&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131205 Semantic Web Research - About a better layered semantic structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5816861850800791555&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131212 Semantic Web Research - How about a noSPARQL and noLinked Data movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5817207331682816002&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131213 Semantic Web Research - Linked Data, an unnecessarily complicated technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/2085042/2085042-5817215079413747713&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131213 NoSQL - How about a noSPARQL and noLinked Data movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/3750024/3750024-5817216825900965891&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131213 Chief Information Security Officer - How about a noSPARQL&amp;hellip;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/2552968/2552968-5817217868823031811&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131213 Graph Databases - How about a noSPARQL and noLinked Data movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5819436988985540612&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131219 Semantic Web Research - Retrofitting, the reality, (CubeWeb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5827030802524827648&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140109 Semantic Web Research - The best debate ever in computer science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-5827044890873208832&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140109 Topic Maps Community - The best debate ever in computer science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5847683290588282884&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140307 Semantic Web Research - R3DM All right, All right, All right&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5847725615553212419&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140307 Semantic Web Research - Data and metadata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5862218105228394497&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140416 Semantic Web Research - R3DM Conceptual Model Explained&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5862220749883850752&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140416 Semantic Web Research - R3DM a glimpse from the future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5862565206613323778&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140417 Computational Semiotics - R3DM A computational semiotics interpretation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5866677067252277249&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140428 Computational Semiotics - R3DM An explanation of the identity crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5866694831748706308&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140428 Semantic Web Research - R3DM An explanation of the identity crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5867387764193927171&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140430 Semantic Web Research - Something very big is coming Wolfram Language&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5870361376756637699&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140509 Semantic Web Research - Linked Data vs Linked Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5883270314305028098&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140613 Computational Semiotics - Information vs Plerophoria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5883147163483013124&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140613 Computational Semiotics - First Attempt to Formalise R3DM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5883182557104742403&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140613 Semantic Web Research - R3DM Formalization v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5884640137274499075&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140617 Semantic Web Research - R3DM Formalization v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5884629742212128772&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140617 Computational Semiotics - R3DM Formalization v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/41001/41001-5889035439259553793&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140617 Functional Programming - Best paradigm for implementing R3DM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5889047044898717696&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140629 Semantic Web Research - Crossroad of Database, Functional Programming and Semantics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5901305361410846723&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140802 Semantic Web Research - The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/62614/62614-5901305006312685571&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140802 Mathematica Users - The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/37945/37945-5901306328223092737&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140802 Artificial Intelligence - The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-5901310366939377667&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140802 Topic Maps Community - The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5901292520796618753&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140802 Computational Semiotics - R3DM perspective on Wolfram Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/2099362/2099362-5910345937716281345&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140802 Greek IT Network - The Threefold Tower of Babel in Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-5926423771366846465&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141010 Topic Maps Community - R3DM: A new paradigm on data modelling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5926425191910510594&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141010 Semantic Web Research - R3DM: A new paradigm on data modelling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/62614/62614-5926429468590637059&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141010 Mathematica Users - R3DM: A new paradigm on data modelling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/62614/62614-5931025523416268801&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141023 Mathematica Users - The Role of Mathematica in semantic technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5932579789884919812&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141027 Semantic Web Research - Semantic Web Research in a poetic style&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5933416099717607425&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141030 Semantic Web Research - AtomicDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5935020264617185285&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141103 Semantic Web Research - Connecting values at an atomic level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/3750024/3750024-5935026662285541379&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141103 Chief Information Security Officer - New paradigm for data modelling in the NoSQL world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5935060245876342788&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141103 Semantic Web Research - An unusual criticism on RDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5935481161441648643&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141104 Semantic Web Research - RDF is that the most basic data model you can think about&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/62614/62614-5935484136608268289&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141104 Mathematica Users - Symbolic expressions in mathematica and the RDF model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/2085042/2085042-5935641835354484737&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141105 NoSQL - Direct linking of two nodes with bidirectional pointers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5942557803641073668&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141124 Computational Semiotics - The core terms of R3DM from two perspectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5942559799718748161&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141124 Computational Semiotics - R3DM Trilateral Relations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5942584139847868418&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141124 Computational Semiotics - R3DM Principles The Dogma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5942593120347652098&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141124 Semantic Web Research - R3DM The core mechanism of abstraction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5955740180148162562&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20141230 Semantic Web Research - R3DM What do we really miss in data modelling field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-6248454510424006661&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20170317 Computational Semiotics - S3DM/R3DM Triangle of Meaning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>S3DM/R3DM Q&amp;A</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/post/20131001/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/post/20131001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#qa-session-on-r3dms3dm&#34;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A session on R3DM/S3DM&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-information&#34;&gt;What is information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-an-information-resource&#34;&gt;What is an information resource&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-kind-of-information-resources-we-have&#34;&gt;What kind of information resources we have&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-an-information-reference&#34;&gt;What is an information reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-information-representation&#34;&gt;What is information representation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-information-realization&#34;&gt;What is information realization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-semantic-models-like-rdfowl-and-tmdm-are-not-sufficient-for-the-semantic-web&#34;&gt;Why semantic models like RDF/OWL and TMDM are not sufficient for the semantic web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#is-there-an-analogy-of-your-model-with-the-object-oriented-programming-paradigm-where-you-have-reusable-and-composable-structures&#34;&gt;Is there an analogy of your model with the object-oriented programming paradigm where you have reusable and composable structures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#semantic-web-or-the-web-of-linked-data-is-using-uris-to-identify-and-to-address-information-resources-is-there-a-difference-in-your-model&#34;&gt;Semantic web or the web of linked data is using URIs to identify and to address information resources, is there a difference in your model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-the-outmost-objective-with-your-r3dm-data-model&#34;&gt;What is the outmost objective with your R3DM data model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#domain-independent-abstraction-and-kinds-of-relations&#34;&gt;Domain Independent Abstraction and Kinds of Relations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;qa-session-on-r3dms3dm&#34;&gt;Q&amp;amp;A session on R3DM/S3DM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-information&#34;&gt;What is information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greek we call it, (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information#Etymology&#34;&gt;plērophoria&lt;/a&gt;) from πλήρης (plērēs) &amp;ldquo;fully&amp;rdquo; and φέρω (phorein) frequentative of (pherein) to carry through. It means to carry, to convey a message thoroughly, exhaustivelly, in a complete way. It is strongly related to the formation of the message, it depends on the sign vehicle we use to transmit the message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-an-information-resource&#34;&gt;What is an information resource&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a container of information. In the computer world a data container such as a blog, a web address, physical memory, computer hard disk. In the physical world any object can be an information resource.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-kind-of-information-resources-we-have&#34;&gt;What kind of information resources we have&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A binary information resource (&lt;strong&gt;BIR&lt;/strong&gt;) is a container of information about concepts related to the computer world, such as a web page, a file, an email, a database record, a programming variable. A term information resource (&lt;strong&gt;TIR&lt;/strong&gt;) is a more generalized concept than BIR. TIR is extended to cover any term in general including those we use in our daily human to human communication. Both BIR and TIR represent abstract concepts. These are constructs that we use at the semantic, ontological layer of R3DM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-an-information-reference&#34;&gt;What is an information reference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An information reference is the source of information resource. It is where it gets its meaning, it is the place it was originally conceived or defined. Any BIR or TIR is conceived in the human mind in the process of thinking. Therefore it follows naturally that they are referenced accordingly. Human concepts are presented from the sender in a verbal, oral, visual, or written way and are perceived from the receiver. Regarding to the meaning, the semantics of the transmitted information, there is strong connection between the interpretant and the sign vehicle used to carry information. The sign vehicle is strongly dependent on the information reference, i.e. the interpretant. We can have more than one interpretations for the same sign, and likewise any sign is referenced in many ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-information-representation&#34;&gt;What is information representation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us take things from the beginning. We have a concept in a human mind. The concept is presented in some perceivable way with symbols, icons, words, spoken sounds, etc. This represents an object of the real world that we want to talk about. In a computer we use metaphores: for example the desktop environment with files and folders on it. In fact any object of the real world can be represented in many ways on a computer screen: characters, numbers, images, sounds, books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-information-realization&#34;&gt;What is information realization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything that is represented in a computer is in fact encoded in a binary format. Any content, such as text for example, can take many forms but at the end it is stored or transmitted in a binary format. In computers, this is the lowest level of information, it is the data level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-semantic-models-like-rdfowl-and-tmdm-are-not-sufficient-for-the-semantic-web&#34;&gt;Why semantic models like RDF/OWL and TMDM are not sufficient for the semantic web&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First let me make something clear. Semantic web is not the web of linked data, it is simply an approximation. In Web 1.0 and 2.0 we were linking documents, e.g. web documents, files. What is different now, is that we also link structured data, from relational databases, from RDF databases. But we are still in the data level. In my opinion Web 3.0 has to be differentiated from the current web, it has to create a distinct layer on top of the existing linked data layer with its own referencing scheme that can be resolved with the current URI scheme. This will have its own way to define and handle terms, concepts, relations, axioms, rules, the structural components of an ontology. The semantic web, is an ontological web. Everything else should revolve around it, data population, ontology enrichment, subject indexing, searching, matching, sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can not make a significant progress on the &amp;ldquo;semantic web&amp;rdquo;, because there is not a model that combines the three main models of information architecture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The database model (data level - Information Realization),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The programming model (symbol level - Information Representation) and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The semantic model (human level - Information Referencing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there is ongoing research on RDF data model towards a semantic object framework, to bridge the gap between RDF and object-oriented programming and there are also researchers that investigate the mismatch of RDF with graph models and graph databases, especially property graph databases. R3DM is looking into combining those two interpretations of RDF by utilizing a post-relational database and a native object script language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;is-there-an-analogy-of-your-model-with-the-object-oriented-programming-paradigm-where-you-have-reusable-and-composable-structures&#34;&gt;Is there an analogy of your model with the object-oriented programming paradigm where you have reusable and composable structures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the first question that has to be answered, is how we define the fundamental unit of information processing. Remember, in Topic-Maps Data Model everything is a topic. In our writing system, word-lexeme-morpheme, is our fundamental unit. The current progress with graph databases, and the long research with RDF triplets indicate, that indeed, we can define such a unit. Let us call this information node (iNode). The new question you should ask is how exactly these nodes are related. How do we represent relations ? The encoding of information into triplets has started long time ago, both with the Entity-Attribute-Value databases and now with the linked data movement. Although OWL is supposed to bridge the gap between programming and semantic relations, in practise this has never been achieved! A new programming language that will be based on a transparent handling of semantic relations and the corresponding data management is absent. This new programming language must be closely connected to the database layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;semantic-web-or-the-web-of-linked-data-is-using-uris-to-identify-and-to-address-information-resources-is-there-a-difference-in-your-model&#34;&gt;Semantic web or the web of linked data is using URIs to identify and to address information resources, is there a difference in your model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are trying to develop a new, semantic web, layer on top of the previous one, where the document, i.e. web page, file, etc is the basic unit of information. The two layers can communicate with the current web addressing infrastructure but the new layer MUST have its own referencing scheme. A scheme that will be used both for retrieving and updating purposes. The naming/identification issue is also of critical importance here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-the-outmost-objective-with-your-r3dm-data-model&#34;&gt;What is the outmost objective with your R3DM data model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current www is based on content (data) and addressing (hypelinks) and the main founder and visioner of the Web Tim Berner&amp;rsquo;s Lee cries out &amp;ldquo;put the data on the web&amp;rdquo;. But the point is how to represent and link the human knowledge on the web, things like concept maps (Novak), conceptual graphs (Sowa) and these are based on linking concepts, not data. I would like to see the web of linked concepts. I see an obsession in many for machine readable data. The point is how our technology can assist us in making fast and smart decisions, in solving extremely complicate problems of interdisciplinary nature and machine readable data is just part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;domain-independent-abstraction-and-kinds-of-relations&#34;&gt;Domain Independent Abstraction and Kinds of Relations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is fundamental for the improvement of this kind of “Semantic Web”, LinkedData Web, if there is going to be some effort to describe and represent abstraction and relation types. We would not have to deal with such a chaos of alignment and mapping on predicates if there was some generally acceptable template, formula on what kind of Domain Independent Abstractions exist and how we can formulate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my R3DM data model and the work in it, is to define such a schema. I will give you a flavour here with an example that is characteristic of the confusion that exists between two specific generic relation types, (1) inheritance-subtyping and (2) hypernymy-hyponymy. Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1)	Music composition &amp;mdash;- isBroaderThan &amp;mdash;&amp;gt; Sonata&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1)	Sonata &amp;mdash;- isNarrowerThan &amp;mdash;&amp;gt; Music Composition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2)	Music Instrument &amp;mdash;- isHypernymOf &amp;mdash;&amp;gt; Wind Instrument&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2)	Wind Instrument &amp;mdash;- isHyponymOf &amp;mdash;&amp;gt; Music Instrument&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that both relations are symmetric and we need to define both directions. Each entity plays also a specific role in that relation. Now, if we can find a consistent way to describe relations that will make life much easier for both the developers and the researchers in “Semantic Web” area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, we can define three broad classes of hierarchical relations that create all kinds of taxonomies (read more about them in other recent posts in this group).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generalization-Specialization expressed with the predicates
nulon:isBroaderThan and nulon:isNarrowerThan and the roles Superior, Subordinate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyponymy-Hypernymy expressed with the predicates
nulon:isHypernymOf and nulon:isHyponymOf and the roles Hypernym, Hyponym&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holonymy-Meronymy expressed with the predicates
nulon:isWholeOf and nulon:isPartOf and the roles Whole, Part&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Triples can be seen as binary predicates, but n-ary relations is a very natural way of thinking about many things such as events. This is exactly the point of a big divergence among TopicMapDM, RelationalDM, GraphPropertyDM, Freebase DM, Associative DM, RDF/OWL DM and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think modelling n-ary relations is not the root of the problem. The mother of all problems in data modelling is the bootstrap mechanism of creating types and the absence of a single universal Upper Level Ontology as the gold standard to define core basic types. Take Freebase for example, they have defined from scratch their own type system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This again cannot be seen in isolation of the data structures, a low level issue, that one is using to permanently store or process the data. This is why I insist that software engineers have to think in at least three perspectives of R3DM semiotic data model, i.e. the semantic, the symbolic and the storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/2099362/2099362-228909136&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130403 Greek IT Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-275236266&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130920 Topic Maps Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-277065814&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130927 Semantic Web Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5812169398596702208&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131129 Computational Semiotics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5822403300636532737&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131227 Semantic Web Research - Domain Independent Abstraction and Kinds of Relations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-5823055552451743745&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131229 Semantic Web Research - Taxonomy Relations - My perspective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5932586289760079874&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20131129 Computational Semiotics - About Binary and N-ary relations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origins of a new theoretical framework on information representation</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/post/20130403/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/post/20130403/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#information-resources-and-real-world-objects&#34;&gt;Information Resources and Real-World Objects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#origins-of-a-new-theoretical-framework-on-information-representation&#34;&gt;Origins of a new theoretical framework on information representation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;information-resources-and-real-world-objects&#34;&gt;Information Resources and Real-World Objects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The distinguishing characteristic of these resources is that all of their essential characteristics can be conveyed in a message. We identify this set as information resources&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume we accept this definition for &amp;ldquo;information resources&amp;rdquo;. Let us take a real apple. Then we ask ourselves, is that apple an information resource according to the previous definition. In my opinion, the answer is No. Because &lt;strong&gt;we cannot convey all the essential characteristics&lt;/strong&gt; of an apple in a message, even if the message is transmitted through conventional human to human communication channels. If someone has not tasted an apple before then you cannot convey that characteristic in a message. One has to eat the apple to learn about that characteristic and many more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, many will be familiar with pictures like the following one from artist Rene Magritte showing a pipe and underneath a text message in French saying &amp;ldquo;this is not a pipe&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well this is not a pipe indeed, it is an information resource about a pipe. To be more specific this is a visual representation (image encoding) of a pipe. Or you may also say we present graphically, we draw a pipe. It is something that refers to a real pipe, but it is not the pipe. In fact, no matter what is the volume of information you are going to use about a real pipe, you will never manage to convey the &lt;strong&gt;true&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;full&lt;/strong&gt; meaning of what a pipe is. But enen in the case we approach a very detailed description of something, then the main obstacle is the interpretant and the interpretation of the message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a more recent effort of W3C to distinguish between digital information resources and real-world object &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/cooluris/#semweb&#34;&gt;it uses URIs to identify both of them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Semantic Web, URIs identify not just Web documents, but also real-world objects like people and cars, and even abstract ideas and non-existing things like a mythical unicorn. We call these real-world objects or things&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is part of a bigger problem due to the inherited weak logic, theory and definitions that support RDF data model. The reader can search for many of these discussions that have appeared on the web under the search term &amp;ldquo;web identity crisis&amp;rdquo;. I believe the root of the problem lies on the inadequate meaning of word information as it is expressed in English. Linguists are aware of the distinction between signifier and signified and Greek language is serving well that purpose as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information#Etymology&#34;&gt;the word &amp;ldquo;plērophoria&amp;rdquo; (signifier) conveys better the meaning of the word &amp;ldquo;information&amp;rdquo; (signified)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ancient Greek word for information is πληροφορία, which transliterates (plērophoria) from πλήρης (plērēs) &amp;ldquo;fully&amp;rdquo; and φέρω (phorein) frequentative of (pherein) to carry through. It literally means &amp;ldquo;bears fully&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;conveys fully&amp;rdquo;. In modern Greek the word Πληροφορία is still in daily use and has the same meaning as the word information in English. In addition to its primary meaning, the word Πληροφορία as a symbol has deep roots in Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s semiotic triangle. In this regard it can be interpreted to communicate information to the one decoding that specific type of sign.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;origins-of-a-new-theoretical-framework-on-information-representation&#34;&gt;Origins of a new theoretical framework on information representation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose a new theoretical framework that will cover RDF/OWL and Topic Map data models, the EAV model in RDBMS and the object-attribute-value model in OOP. So far there have been very weak attempts to bridge the gap among the Semantic Web, the Relational Databases world, the Object-Oriented programming community and recently the NoSQL Databases arena. All these need a solid theoretical framework that unifies them and an implementation that exhibits that these technologies are simply different perspectives of the same approach to information representation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/2099362/2099362-228909136&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130403 Greek IT Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/109285/109285-228701193&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130403 Topic Maps Community &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/38506/38506-228707355&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130403 Semantic Technologies &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/129217/129217-228708177&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130403 Semantic Web Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/45183/45183-228710356&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20130403 Database Experts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/6514034/6514034-5883270314305028098&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20140613 Computational Semiotics - Information vs Plerophoria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/plerophoria-vs-information-athanassios-i-hatzis-phd/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20150523 Article - Plerophoria vs Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture of the WWW, W3C Recommendation 15/12/2004, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/#id-resources&#34;&gt;section 2.2 URI/Resource Relationships&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool URIs for the Semantic Web, W3C Interest Group Note 3/12/2008, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/cooluris/#semweb&#34;&gt;section 3 URIs for Real-World Objects&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information#Etymology&#34;&gt;Etymology section&lt;/a&gt; of the term Information was updated by user Healis with the quoted text above on the 13th of June 2014 &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
