<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tagline on HEALIS</title>
    <link>https://healis.eu/en/tags/tagline/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tagline on HEALIS</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; HEALIS - Athanassios I. Hatzis, {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://healis.eu/en/tags/tagline/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Build valuable relations; establish effective communications</title>
      <link>https://healis.eu/en/post/20180305/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://healis.eu/en/post/20180305/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;why----how----what&#34;&gt;Why &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; How &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; What&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simon Sinek discovered that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/simon_sinek_how_great_leaders_inspire_action&#34;&gt;all great companies think, act and communicate the exact same way&lt;/a&gt; and he illustrated the method with the following infographic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://emmelinefarrell.blogspot.gr/2016/02/essay-research-simon-sinek-ted-talk.html&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;jpg&#34; src=&#34;./golden_circle.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years I have been working on a personal project that started with research on data modeling and now it reached the level of a database add-on product. And without realizing it, I have just discovered, that &lt;strong&gt;I was always working from the inside out&lt;/strong&gt; but I could not articulate why until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information technology is a tool that can be used in many ways, but perhaps the most creative and imaginative aspect, is to &lt;strong&gt;view IT as the vehicle for communication&lt;/strong&gt;. In that case IT covers a basic human need, arguably a need that can be even more important than food. And communication in Greek is ΕΠΙ-ΚΟΙΝΩΝΙΑ, literally meaning, on top of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Man is by nature a political animal&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;relations-and-communications&#34;&gt;Relations and Communications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can easily see what one can achieve with a computer, but deep behind this behavior is the &lt;strong&gt;why part of it&lt;/strong&gt;. Take internet for example, you can educate yourself, you can learn about something new, you can interact with systems and services, you can be creative. This is definitely a form of communication. But it is more direct when you become a member in a social media site, or in a forum, or in a programming/game community. And the reason behind all these user actions is that &lt;strong&gt;we need to communicate&lt;/strong&gt;. We need customers to serve, we need an audience to perform, we need others to share things, we need to be in a group of people. We are internet citizens, citizens of this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is would you travel around the world without any navigation system ? Same question is true for internet. It is the search engine and the hyperlinks that play partly the role of a map and a compass. But nowadays these are not enough. It&amp;rsquo;s because we have started asking to get meaning, to find value out of our data. We want to understand not only how but why things are interconnected. Therefore we should &lt;strong&gt;use technology, the know how, to build meaningful, valuable relationships and lay them down as a foundation to establish effective communication&lt;/strong&gt;. And in my opinion, and opinion of great inspired leaders you have to think, act and communicate from inside out. &lt;strong&gt;It is not the product that defines the need, it is the need that dictates what is the product&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the right guide in the design and implementation of inter-operable systems, devices and applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-see-things-differently&#34;&gt;We see things differently&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In HEALIS this is our philosophy and also our brand strategy to develop great solutions to fully cover your needs and the needs of your customers. A humble start was made with &lt;a href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/triadb/&#34;&gt;TRIADB&lt;/a&gt;. Although &lt;a href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/project/triadb/&#34;&gt;TRIADB&lt;/a&gt; is not a product for the common end-user, it reflects &lt;a href=&#34;https://healis.eu/en/post/20150523/&#34;&gt;our way of thinking about information&lt;/a&gt; technology in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mtftHaK9tYY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s to the crazy ones. The misfits. The rebels. The troublemakers. The round pegs in the square holes. The ones who see things differently. They&amp;rsquo;re not fond of rules. And they have no respect for the status quo. You can quote them, disagree with them, glorify or vilify them. About the only thing you can&amp;rsquo;t do is ignore them. Because they change things. They push the human race forward. And while some may see them as the crazy ones, we see genius. Because the people who are crazy enough to think they can change the world, are the ones who do &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have laid strong foundations, we put the cornerstone at the right place. We made a start and we can see the future of this. If you, want to learn why, we know how and what you will get is the fulfillment of our common goal:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;button class=&#34;btn  btn-warning&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;  &gt; Build valuable relations; establish effective communications &lt;/button&gt;



&lt;h2 id=&#34;cross-references&#34;&gt;Cross-References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/healis-build-valuable-relations-establish-effective-hatzis/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn - 20180305 Pulse Article - HEALIS: Build valuable relations; establish effective communications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs, Apple advertisement (Aired 1997)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
